<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-richardson-anima-bootstrap-state-considerations-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="anima-bootstrap-state">Considerations for stateful vs stateless join router in ANIMA bootstrap</title>

    <author fullname="Michael C. Richardson" initials="M."
            surname="Richardson">
      <organization abbrev="SSW">Sandelman Software Works</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>470 Dawson Avenue</street>

          <city>Ottawa</city>

          <region>ON</region>

          <code>K1Z 5V7</code>

          <country>CA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mcr+ietf@sandelman.ca</email>

        <uri>http://www.sandelman.ca/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2016"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document explores a number of issues affecting the decision to
        use a stateful or stateless forwarding mechanism by the join router (aka join assistant) during the bootstrap process for ANIMA.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title=" Introduction">
      <!-- 1, line 116-->

      <t>The <xref target="I-D.pritikin-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra" />
      defines a process to securely enroll new devices in an existing network.
      It order to avoid providing globally reachable addresses to the
      prospective new network member, it assumes that a Join Router.
      The role of this router is common in this kind of architecture.
      </t>
      <section title=" Terminology">
        <t>
          EAP <xref target="RFC5247" />, 802.1X and PANA <xref target="RFC5191" />
          use the term Authenticator to refer this role.
        </t>
        <t>
        The Thread architecture <xref target="threadcommish" /> uses the term
        Joiner Router</t>
        <t>
          The 6tisch architecture (<xref target="I-D.ietf-6tisch-terminology"/>)
          uses the term JA, short for Join Assistant.
        </t>
        
      </section>

      <!-- ends: "1.1 from line 149-->
    </section>

    <!-- ends: "1 from line 116-->
    <section title="Purpose of the Joiner Router/Join Assistant">

      <t>This device is one layer-2 hop from the new device.  In addition to
      whatever secured networks it might connect to, it runs 
      a sufficiently unprotected network (either physical or wireless) such
      that a new device can connect at layer-2 without any specific
      credentials.</t>
      
      <t>
        The new node runs a discovery protocol as explained in
        <xref target="I-D.pritikin-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra" />
        to find an address for a registrar to which it can run the
        Enrollment over Secure Transport (EST, <xref target="RFC7030" />.
        EST runs RESTfully over protocols such as HTTP.
      </t>

      <t>
        The new node does not have a globally routable address, so it can not
        speak directly outside the current link.  This an intentional
        limitation so that the new node can neither be easily attacked from
        the general internet, nor can it attack arbitrary parts of the
        Internet.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Joiner Router provides a limited channel between the new node,
        and the Registrar.  This document is about the various options and
        considerations that need to be considered when chosing this limited
        channel.
      </t>
      <t>       
        An additional goal of this document is to outline which methods could
        be interchangeably be used by private negotiation between the Joining
        Router and the Registar, without the knowledge of the New Node.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title=" Security Considerations">

      <t>STUFF</t>
    </section>


  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5191" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5247" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7030" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.pritikin-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-6tisch-terminology" ?>>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="threadcommish"
                 target="http://threadgroup.org/Portals/0/documents/whitepapers/Thread%20Commissioning%20white%20paper_v2_public.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Thread Commissioning</title>
          <author surname="Thread Consortium"></author>
          <date month="Jul" year="2015" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <!--  -->
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>

